Register of the Vitaliĭ Leonidovich Kataev papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Electronic Files, 1991-2001 (Box 15)
  - Disk02, 1991-2001; Bulk, 2001
    -Structure of specialists working in the production of arms and military technology in the USSR
    -Quantity of strategic arms in 1990 September
    -Data on WTO conventional weapons
    -Report on personal activity in "Yuzhnoe" and the "pyatyorka"
    -Security Council materials
    -Perfection of military-technical cooperation with foreign countries
    -Correspondence with Gorbachev, the government, and Marshal Akhromeev
    -Problems of VPK conversion in the USSR
    -Materials for directives for negotiations
    -Issues of the formation of the military budget in the USSR
    -Zaikov's report on the consequences of concluding an INF treaty
    -Perfection of practice in preparing materials for negotiations regarding military-political issues
    -Telephones of the participants in the work of the Inter-Departmental Working Group ("pyatyorka") and the Politburo Commission (higher "pyatyorka")
    -Re-equipment of heavy bombers Tu-95MC
    -CPSU CC report regarding charges of participating in the proliferation of chemical weapons made against the USSR
    -Working group for issues of military-technical cooperation with Afghanistan
    -Argumentation regarding issues of increasing openness
    -Consultations with the USA on chemical weapons
    -Draft CPSU CC resolution on the reduction of armed forces and expenses for defense in the USSR
    -Correspondence with Zaikov
    -Status of negotiations on nuclear testing
    -Outline on the reduction of conventional arms in Europe
    -Table showing expenses on weapons in various countries of the world
    -Tactical rocket "Oka"
    -Problems of tactical rockets in Europe
    -USSR Security Council documents
    -Correspondence of the state advisor for conversion with Yeltsin
    -Description of the concern "Binitek"
    -Documents on the joint-stock company Business Center-VPK (BTs-VPK); correspondence with the government regarding issues of the organization of BTs-VPK
    -Participants in the conference in Moscow on conversion in space, 1992
    -Correspondence with the chairman of the Expert Council under the president of Russia, O. I. Lobov, regarding problems of relations with Taiwan
    -Description of joint stock company Military-Industrial Investment Company
    -Correspondence of the state advisor for conversion, M. D. Malei, regarding issues of the organization of the BTs-VPK
    -Orders regarding BTs-VPK
    -Correspondence regarding issues of military-technical cooperation, in particular with Brazil
    -Materials of the organization loan credit for a deposit for the use of rare metals
    -Materials of the BTs-VPK
    -Specifications of aerodynamic pipes TsAGI
    -Documents on commercial ties of BTs-VPK with foreign firms
    - A.TXT
    - AFGAN-B.TXT
    - AFGAN-C.TXT
    - AFGAN-D.TXT
    - AFGAN-F.TXT
    - AFGAN.TXT
    - AFRIC2.TXT
    - AFRICA.TXT
    - AGENSTVO.TXT
    - ARGENT.TXT
    - ARGENT1.TXT
    - ARGENT2.TXT
    - ARGENT4.TXT
    - ARGUM.TXT
    - AT-KHP.TXT
    - AUTO
    - AXPOM.TXT
    - B.TXT
    - BAC-20.05
    - BARO-TIR.TXT
    - BATAREI.TXT
    - BAZALT.TXT
    - BC-GAID.TXT
    - BC-GAIDA.TXT
    - BC-MALEI.TXT
    - BC-MIC.TXT
    - BC-OWDNA.TXT
    - BC-PETRO.TXT
    - BC-UKAZ.TXT
    - BCE.TXT
    - BEHA-3OH.TXT
    - BINITEC1.TXT
    - BKC-ANGL.TXT
    - BKC-IMPE.TXT
    - BKC-ISSL.TXT
    - BRAZIL.TXT
    - CHARGE.TXT
    - COKP-BPK.TXT
    - COKPA.TXT
    - COMIS-AF.TXT
    - CONCEP.TXT
    - CONCEPT1.TXT
    - CONFER.TXT
    - CONV-CB.TXT
    - CONV-CB1.TXT
    - CTATJA.TXT
    - DEPOZIT.TXT
    - DEPOZIT2.TXT
    - DEPOZIT3.TXT
    - DEPOZIT4.TXT
    - DEPOZIT5.TXT
    - DGIP.TXT
    - DNEPR.TXT
    - DOKLAD.TXT
    - DOL-INST.TXT
    - DOL-MSG.TXT
    - ELEK-NAV.TXT
    - ENERGO.TXT
    - EU-TACT.TXT
    - EUR-ARSE.TXT
    - EURO-SEC.TXT
    - EURO-TOL.TXT
    - EXPERT.TXT
    - F-16.TXT
    - FILATOV.TXT
    - FOND.TXT
    - GAS-SAHA.TXT
    - GDR-ZAJA.TXT
    - GERMAN.TXT
    - GERMAN2.TXT
    - GERMAN3.TXT
    - GIBRID.TXT
    - GLUHIH.TXT
    - GLUHIH2.TXT
    - GOSSOVET.TXT
    - HAINS.TXT
    - HIGA-BKC.TXT
    - IMPORT.TXT
    - INTERVJU.TXT
    - IRAN-BTC.TXT
    - ITAL-2.TXT
    - ITALIA.TXT
    - KADRI.TXT
    - KOHBEP1.TXT
    - KOHBEPC2.TXT
    - KOMSOMOL.TXT
    - KP-AXPOM.TXT
    - KP-DOKL.TXT
    - KP-HAKO.TXT
    - KP-HATO.TXT
    - KP-NAVU.TXT
    - KP-USA1.TXT
    - KP-USA2.TXT
    - KP-USA3.TXT
    - KRB.TXT
    - KUBA-BTC.TXT
    - LEW-100.PRN
    - LEW-COMI.TXT
    - LEW-KOM2.TXT
    - LEW-KOM3.TXT
    - LEW-KOM4.TXT
    - LEW-KOM5.TXT
    - LEW-TEZI.TXT
    - LOBOV.TXT
    - MAL-DOLG.TXT
    - MALEI-1.TXT
    - MALEI-10.TXT
    - MALEI-2.TXT
    - MALEI-7.TXT
    - MALEI-8.TXT
    - MANADGER.TXT
    - MEMORAND.TXT
    - MOBIL.TXT
    - MSG-14.TXT
    - MSG-PRED.TXT
    - NU-ISP.TXT
    - NUC-EURO.TXT
    - NUCLEAR.TXT
    - OKA-EURO.TXT
    - OKA-OWD.TXT
    - OKLAD.TXT
    - OKLAD2.TXT
    - OLEG-1.TXT
    - OPEN-SKY.TXT
    - OPLATA.TXT
    - OTD-CON.TXT
    - PAB-GR.TXT
    - PAB-GRUP.TXT
    - PACXOD.TXT
    - PCD-INFO.TXT
    - PCMD.TXT
    - PEREZEN.TXT
    - PETROV-1.TXT
    - PETROV-2.TXT
    - PHILIP.TXT
    - PLAN.TXT
    - POLOGEN-.TXT
    - POLOGEN2.TXT
    - POLOGEN3.TXT
    - POLOGEN4.TXT
    - POLOGEN5.TXT
    - POPRAVKA.PRN
    - PR-PACP.TXT
    - PRAVDA.TXT
    - PRESS1.TXT
    - PRESS2.TXT
    - PRESS3.TXT
    - PRESSA-1.TXT
    - PRESSA.TXT
    - PROECT.TXT
    - PROEK-UK.TXT
    - PROEKTI.TXT
    - REDACTIR.TXT
    - RSMD-2.TXT
    - RSMD.TXT
    - SILAEV.TXT
    - SKOKOV-1.TXT
    - SKOKOV-3.TXT
    - SKOKOV-4.TXT
    - SKOKOV-5.TXT
    - SKOKOV-6.TXT
    - SKOKOV-7.TXT
    - SLUGBA.TXT
    - SOI-PRES.TXT
    - SOI-PRO.TXT
    - SPECIAL.TXT
    - STAROVOI.TXT
    - STRUCTUR.TXT
    - SU-3AJAB.TXT
    - SU-COTP.TXT
    - SURIKJV.TXT
    - TABL-1
    - TABL-2
    - TABL-4
    - TACTIC.TXT
    - TACTIC1.TXT
    - TEL-GERM.TXT
    - TEZIS2.TXT
    - TOP-TEXH.TXT
    - TRUDI.TXT
    - TU-95.TXT
    - UKAZ.TXT
    - ULJANOVS.TXT
    - UOLLES.TXT
    - UTILIZAZ.TXT
    - VKS-ANGL.TXT
    - VPIC.TXT
    - XIM.TXT
    - Z.TXT
    - ZAJAVL.TXT
    - ZELENOGR.TXT
  - Disk03, 1993-2001; Bulk, 2001
    -Participants in the Cold War (regarding a conference?)
    -Rolodex of enterprises
    -Proposals on the organization of a VPK consortium
    -Correspondence with the firm IMBEL (Brazil)
    -Correspondence with the government regarding issues of cooperation with Brazil
    -Issues of insuring scientific research work
    -Particulars of the military-industrial potential of Ukraine and the prospects of military-technical cooperation
    -Organization of a series of technological products based on the helicopter Mi-8
    -Correspondence of BTs-VPD with the government and banks
    -Materials regarding technology for reprocessing old automobile tires
    -Summary data on VPK enterprises in Perm
    -Questions for preparation for a conference (a USA proposal) regarding technologies for the control of non-proliferation of weapons of mass destruction
    -Correspondence with departments--draft of a memo
    -Correspondence regarding commercial issues with representatives of the USSR Academy of Sciences in the USA
    -Problems in new technology for the dismantling of atomic submarines into metal
    -Organization of a visit of representatives of Lockheed to TsNIIMash
    -List of institutes for research on the strategic development of weapons and military technology
    -Data on the space system
    -An overview of the VPK
    -Report on personal activity--draft of dissertation
    -Analysis of factors that determine the interrelationship of the armed forces and the VPK in conditions of transition to the market economy
    -Analysis of the condition of Ukraine's VPK
    -Draft memoir materials about Kataev's own activity, in particular recounting the activity of the military-technological engineers and developers M. K. Yangel and V. P. Makeev
    -Materials on cooperation with Brazil
    -A contract with "Defense Export" (OboronEksport)
    -Commercial projects
    -On export controls
    -Correspondence with the government
    -Proposals on cooperation in space technology with Italy
    -Main institute for space rocket technology TSNIIMash
    -VPK plants in Perm
    -Personal memo regarding the reason for limiting travel abroad
    -Materials on the organization of a Russian-Hungarian society
    -Questionnaire for research (with the Institute "Phoenix," USA) regarding Cold War issues
    -Strategic nuclear rocket and other weapons in Ukraine
    -Personal correspondence regarding questions of limiting travel abroad
    -Materials for a report
    -Memoir materials
    -Research materials on the experience of forming scientific-technology policy in the area of weapons development
    -Materials for a speech at the Duma
    -Article on mobile rocket complex
    -Materials on prognostication methodology
    -Formation of the management of development of new technology
    -Research materials on the basis of forming science and technology policy in the sphere of national security
    -Draft proposal, "Bases of Forming Science and Technology Policy in the Sphere of National Security"
    -Analysis of the condition and prospects of the development of infrastructure, fuel and energy base of the VPK
    -Use of experience in the formation of science-technology policy in the sphere of national security in the leading countries of the world
    -Development of military scientific research in Western Europe
    -On the system of the approach in the USA toward making decisions
    -Problems regarding SDI
    -Disagreements on issues of arms limitations
    -Problems of military policy in the late 1980s
    - BTC.TXT
    - COI.TXT
    - DOKL.TXT
    - DUMA.TXT
    - GLU-2.TXT
    - GLU-3-1.TXT
    - GLU-3.TXT
    - GLU-4.TXT
    - GLU-5.TXT
    - GLU-6.TXT
    - GLUBO.TXT
    - LOBOV.TXT
    - MALEI-10.TXT
    - MODUL.TXT
    - MODUL6.TXT
    - MOTOR-1.TXT
    - NASOS2
    - OTZET-2B.TXT
    - OTZET.TXT
    - PAZNOGL.TXT
    - REDKO.TXT
    - SIDOR3A
    - TEHNOLOG.TXT
    - V-KAZAN2.TXT
    - ZAL-GLU.TXT
    - ZAL-SB.TXT
    - ZAL-UKAZ.TXT
    - ZALOG
  - Disk04, 1993-2001
    -On the consortium of VPK enterprises
    -Materials on the condition of the VPK
    -Draft of an electricity plant based on the use of aviation engines working on natural gas
    -Proposal of South Korea on the construction of a helicopter
    -Correspondence with the power ministries regarding a principally new focus for firearms
    -Concept of a space system
    -Correspondence with the government regarding the structure for working out proposals
    -Correspondence with the administration of the president of the Russian Federation regarding the issue of permission to travel abroad--materials for reports to the United Nations
    -Materials for project for the application of beryllium for the equipping of hard magnetic disks and other computer components that significantly improve the consumer quality of computers (speed of access and memory capacity by 2 to 4 times as compared with the aluminum components used at present)
    -Article on recycling of worn-out tires
    -Materials for the TV broadcast about sunken chemical weapons of the World War II period
    -Concept for the liquidation of the danger presented by the German chemical weapons of World War II in the Gulfs of Scaherak (?) and Kattegut (?)
    -Methodology of prognostication
    -Materials about Ukraine
    -Materials for the project for equipment for recycling worn-out tires
    -Project for the use of the composite material on the basis of basaltic fibers for the construction reinforcement with an improved module elasticity and strength against aggressive environments
    -Project for a miniature signaling indicator for individual use for determining the presence of harsh ultraviolet rays of the sun that create conditions of cancer risk
    -Participants of the Cold War (a conference?)
    -Commission for negotiations on the limitation of arms
    -Overview of the VPK
    -Chart on the organization of high-level decisions in the USSR
    -List of drafts for Defense Ministry of Great Britain
    -VPK materials
    -Several CPSU issues
    -Materials of the CPSU CC Defense Industry Department
    -Military-technical cooperation
    -Defense Council under the USSR President Gorbachev
    -USSR Presidential Council
    -Concept for an outer space system "Earth-Space-Earth"
    -Project VITA for the use of heavy rocket SS-18 for the creation of a global system for rendering emergency rescue assistance
    -Projects of the machine-building plant V. P. Makeev for the creation of strategic rocket complexes on submarines
    -Materials from interviews "VPK USSR - The [View?] From Inside"
    -Correspondence regarding railroad rocket deployment and transport system "Dvigatelei N. K. Kuznetsova"
    -Possible directions for the development of space systems
    -Methodology for prognosticating potential directions in the development of the possible creation of new technologies for guaranteeing Russia's national security
    -Principles of the formation of systems of management for the development of the newest technologies in the condition of budget limitations
    -Chart of the organization of work for the preparation of decisions regarding military-political problems of the USSR in the second half of the 1980s
    -Materials on BTs VPK
    - 80-90.TXT
    - AEROKOS.DWG
    - AFGAN.TXT
    - AVIA-OBR.TXT
    - BARO-L.TXT
    - BASALT-L.TXT
    - BKC-CPA.TXT
    - BKC-STA.TXT
    - BOAT-L.TXT
    - BOLIVIJA.TXT
    - BOPOH1-L.TXT
    - BRPL-HIS.TXT
    - BTC.TXT
    - CAMAPA.TXT
    - CAMAPA1.TXT
    - CAMAPA2.TXT
    - COL-ARMS.TXT
    - COLDWEP.TXT
    - COMISSIA.TXT
    - CONVERS.TXT
    - COSMOS.TXT
    - CTOL.TXT
    - CTPYKTY3.TXT
    - CTPYKTYP.TXT
    - DEF-IND.TXT
    - DINO2.TXT
    - DISK-1.TXT
    - DUMA-1.TXT
    - ECO-SEA2.TXT
    - ECO-TAS2.TXT
    - ELEKTRO1.TXT
    - ESSE.TXT
    - F-KOKO.TXT
    - F-KULIK.TXT
    - F-NIKOL.TXT
    - F-RODIO2.TXT
    - F-XIM1.TXT
    - FAMILI3
    - FEDOS-S3.TXT
    - FEDOS-SP.TXT
    - FILTR.TXT
    - FOND-2.TXT
    - FONDPRE2.TXT
    - FONDPRES.TXT
    - G4.$$$
    - GK492051.TMP
    - GON.TXT
    - GON1.TXT
    - INF2.TXT
    - INF3.TXT
    - INFORM.TXT
    - IS.TXT
    - KADRI.TXT
    - KERAMIC.TXT
    - KOK-6.TXT
    - KOMAND.TXT
    - KONSORC
    - KPSS.TXT
    - KUMERTAU.TXT
    - KUZMA1.TXT
    - LEBED-2.TXT
    - LEBED-4.TXT
    - LOBOV.TXT
    - MASLUK-4.TXT
    - MATR.TXT
    - MEMORAND.TXT
    - MIC.TXT
    - MIHEEV.TXT
    - NAKOPL.TXT
    - NOI-7.TXT
    - NOI-BET.TXT
    - OKA-1.TXT
    - OTZET-3.TXT
    - PACX.TXT
    - PLAKAT.TXT
    - POTENZ.TXT
    - PROGNOZ.TXT
    - PS.TXT
    - RESURS.TXT
    - SHINA-2.TXT
    - SO.TXT
    - SOC.TXT
    - SOL-DF2.TXT
    - TABL.TXT
    - TAKE-OU.TXT
    - TEHNO.TXT
    - TREB.TXT
    - TROFIM-1.TXT
    - TV-1.TXT
    - TV-10.TXT
    - TV-13.TXT
    - TV-14.TXT
    - TV-15.TXT
    - TV-18.TXT
    - TV-19.TXT
    - TV-2.TXT
    - TV-4.TXT
    - TV-5.TXT
    - TV-6.TXT
    - TV-7.TXT
    - TV-8.TXT
    - TV-9.TXT
    - TY-4.TXT
    - UGROZA.TXT
    - VGA-1.TXT
    - VGA-LAT.TXT
    - VGA-MVD2.TXT
    - VITA-L.TXT
    - VKS-2.TXT
    - VKS-3.TXT
    - VOLGA6.TXT
    - WK272646.TMP
    - XB-2.TXT
    - XB.TXT
    - ZAKON-2.TXT
  - Disk05, 1992-2001
    -Materials for space systems and for a report on space systems
    -Membership of the Politburo Commission for Negotiations with the USA beginning from the 1960s -- excerpts from Politburo resolutions
    -Beginning of VPK conversion and a budget
    -SDI
    -Cold War
    -Commercial drafts
    -Problems of breaking down atomic submarines into metal
    -Contract with enterprises
    -Correspondence with Kokoshin and Soskovets on the conduct of a meeting (on a proposal from the USA) regarding problems of global control for the non-proliferation of weapons of mass destruction
    - A5.TXT
    - AGENT
    - AVIA-OBR.TXT
    - BARO-ANG.TXT
    - BCE.$$$
    - BETAK
    - BIOPR
    - BKC-KA1.TXT
    - BKC-KA2.TXT
    - BKC-KA3.TXT
    - BKC-KA3C.TXT
    - BOLGAR
    - BRASMER
    - BYZK
    - COLD-W.TXT
    - DEF-IND.TXT
    - DIALIZ.TXT
    - DISK-1.TXT
    - DLD1
    - DLD2
    - ELEKTRO1.TXT
    - ELPLITA
    - F-MASLO.TXT
    - FORM-1.TXT
    - FORM-2.TXT
    - FORM-3.TXT
    - GARWARD
    - GASOTURB.TXT
    - GATTNER
    - GENS
    - GRUP-1.TXT
    - GRUPPA3.TXT
    - HOLOD
    - INFRA
    - KALLIST
    - KERAMIC.TXT
    - KOMMER
    - KOMPR1
    - KORD-DEF.TXT
    - LAZER.TXT
    - LEV.NIK
    - LUX
    - MACKA.TXT
    - MAL-ZALO.TXT
    - METON
    - MODUL-A.TXT
    - MOTOR-1.TXT
    - NEFT
    - NERASP
    - NOVTEX
    - OPTIKA
    - PLATEL
    - POLE.TXT
    - RADAR2.TXT
    - S-1.TXT
    - S-10.TXT
    - S-2.TXT
    - S-3.TXT
    - S-4.TXT
    - S-6.TXT
    - S-7.TXT
    - S-8.TXT
    - S-9.TXT
    - S5.TXT
    - SIDOR3A
    - SISKIN2
    - SOI-A.TXT
    - SOL-DEF1.TXT
    - SOL-DEF2.TXT
    - SOLAR-1.TXT
    - SUR
    - TRANS.TXT
    - VGA-5.TXT
    - VKS-AA.TXT
    - VKS-ANOT.TXT
    - VKS-LATI.TXT
    - WATER.TXT
    - ZALOG-ZE.TXT
    - ZALOG.TXT
- Sound Recordings, 1990s (Box 15)
  Original sound cassettes closed. Use copies available in the Hoover Archives reading room.
  Six sound cassettes of interviews of participants in the Cold War from the Soviet Military Industrial Complex (VPK).
  - Mishin, circa 1990
    Use copy reference number: 2002c48_a_0000627
    Side B contains many short stories from the BBC World Service from around December 1990.
  - Chervov, 1993 January 26 (or possibly 28)
    Use copy reference number: 2002c48_a_0000628
  - Kovalev, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2002c48_a_0000629
  - Illarionov, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2002c48_a_0000630
  - Kornienko, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2002c48_a_0000631
  - Strogonov, undated
    Use copy reference number: 2002c48_a_0000632
- Incremental Materials (Boxes 16-20)